Speaker 1: Hey everyone, Peter Zion here, coming to you from central Yosemite, just south of
Speaker 1: Quartzite Peak. This is a very difficult place to get to. In my opinion, the view
Speaker 1: makes it worth it, but it's two days of off-trail travel in the most rugged parts
Speaker 2: of the park. Let's talk about something else that we hope is worth it, and that is
Speaker 2: green tech, solar and wind particularly. Now, photovoltaic cells are... they're
Speaker 2: heralded as a cure-all. The idea is you can put them anywhere, get a little bit of
Speaker 1: juice from the Sun, it's better than any sort of fossil fuels, and that is total
Speaker 1: and absolute crap. The process for producing PVs is extraordinarily damaging
Speaker 1: to the environment if it's done wrong, and even if it's done right, it's a bit of a
Speaker 1: question as to whether or not you can put the panels in the right place. Now, the
Speaker 1: silicon that goes into the PV panels themselves is not hard to get. Silicon is
Speaker 2: one of the more common elements, and you can mine quartz in a lot of places. Then
Speaker 2: there are half a dozen places that can refine it into solar-grade silicon. However,
Speaker 2: that process basically involves a blast furnace, and if you're doing this in
Speaker 2: China, which is where nearly half of it is done, you're talking about doing it with
Speaker 2: coal. So already the carbon footprint for the process is extreme. And then most of
Speaker 2: the assembly for the panels is done in China as well, usually in places like
Speaker 2: Zhejiang where it's done by slave labor. So already you've got all these things
Speaker 2: that are kind of stacking up against solar right from the get-go. Now this is all
Speaker 2: okay, right? If you're able to get an environmental benefit on the back end. Well,
Speaker 2: there are a lot of places in the world that are not particularly sunny, and most of
Speaker 2: those are places where we have our big cities. So for example, here I am in the highlands of
Speaker 2: the Sierras. If I was to put panels here, they'd do really well. We're at high elevation. They have
Speaker 2: a lot of long sun days. It would be fine. Unfortunately, not a lot of people live here.
Speaker 2: Take those same panels, and you move them to Seattle or Toronto or New York or Boston or London or
Speaker 2: Copenhagen or Stockholm or Shanghai or Hong Kong, and they're gonna generate less than
Speaker 2: one-fifth the amount of electricity. So whatever you're willing to suck up on the
Speaker 2: front end, you need those panels to run five times as long in order to make good.
Speaker 2: And in most of those cities that I listed, that means you will never break even on
Speaker 2: just the carbon debt to say nothing of the trade issues or the human rights issues.
Speaker 2: Now, does that mean that solar is pointless and you can't put it anywhere? Of course not.
Speaker 2: If you're going to put it in a sunny place, say Albuquerque, New Mexico, where I live in
Speaker 2: Denver, Durban, South Africa, most places in, say, Italy or Greece, there are a lot of
Speaker 1: places where it makes a lot of sense. But there are far more where it makes none
Speaker 1: whatsoever. And then, of course, there's a transmission issue. You don't put panels in
Speaker 1: New York because it's too densely populated. You have to put them outside of the city, and if you
Speaker 1: want to put them outside the city far enough away that they actually generate a
Speaker 1: meaningful trickle of power, you're talking then about wiring at at least 500
Speaker 1: miles. And now you have another issue with transmission and all the things that go
Speaker 1: with that. So that's solar. Wind. Much better. There's nothing toxic involved in the
Speaker 1: manufacturing. A lot of the manufacturing is either done in the United States or in
Speaker 1: Denmark. You're using some sort of carbon fiber and then some aluminum. There is a
Speaker 1: carbon footprint to both of those, but it's nothing compared to what you have to do
Speaker 1: for silicon. And unlike solar, which seems to have this mystique, wind doesn't. No one
Speaker 1: thinks that they should put wind turbines where it's not windy, but people think
Speaker 1: that they should put solar panels where it's not sunny. And so wind turbines are
Speaker 2: only going up in places that it makes sense. So American Great Plains are great, for
Speaker 2: example. There's some places in California that are good. In the case of Europe,
Speaker 2: anywhere in the vicinity of the North Sea looks great. The Danes get about half of
Speaker 2: their power from wind. And then there are a number of places around the world that
Speaker 1: look good as well. There's still the problem of co-locating that production with
Speaker 1: population centers, but it's not nearly as messy in the case of wind because we're
Speaker 1: now seeing a technological advance with wind. It used to be that the turbines were
Speaker 1: only 100 feet tall. And so unless you had wind right there on the ground, it didn't
Speaker 1: make much sense. But as our engineering has improved, it's gone to 200, 300, 40, now
Speaker 1: almost 800 feet. And that means there's larger parts of the planet. We've seen like a
Speaker 1: quadrupling of zones of the planet where wind now makes sense. And as you reach
Speaker 1: higher, something else happens. You tap wind currents that are not just stronger, that
Speaker 1: are more reliable. I'm going to rotate a little bit here so you can see more of
Speaker 1: the view. That's where I went like four years ago. Anyway, because of that, for per
Speaker 1: dollar invested in wind versus solar, you're going to generate about three to
Speaker 1: four times as much electricity. In addition, those stronger, more reliable
Speaker 1: currents can now start to be used for baseload capacity, which is really
Speaker 1: important. One of the problems we have with wind versus solar and wind versus
Speaker 1: solar versus everything else is intermittency. Obviously, the wind doesn't
Speaker 1: always blow, and there has never been one iota of solar energy generated after
Speaker 1: sunset. And yet, prime demand in most cities in the world is after 6 p.m. for
Speaker 1: electricity. And that means solar can never be part of peak demand, but now wind
Speaker 1: can. So, not only you're getting that three or four to one price difference in
Speaker 1: terms of solar versus wind, wind is actually more useful overall because the
Speaker 1: wind can burn, or sorry, the wind can blow at times when we need the power the
Speaker 1: most. Now, the problem we have is that everyone has believing this mystique on
Speaker 1: solar, and so in most populated zones in most of the planet, solar has become part of
Speaker 1: the environmental problem rather than part of the solution. And until we can get
Speaker 1: past that, until we can actually match technologies to locations, the green
Speaker 1: movement is actually, in many cases, causing more damage than help. Except for
Speaker 1: wind. Wind is great. Okay, that's it for me. Until next time.